In this series of videos, we're going to introduce the ZOS UNIX shell and utilities.
We'll learn how to use some basic shell commands and how to navigate between TSO and the shell.
The shell is the interactive interface to ZOS.
It's part of the ZOS UNIX application services base element of ZOS.
Although some functions can be performed by TSOE,
it's recommended that you make use of the shell and know your way around it.
The shell enables you to invoke shell commands and utilities,
write shell scripts using the shell programming language,
and run shell scripts and C language programs interactively in the background or in batch.
Shell commands are typically short and they can be combined in pipes or shell scripts.
Once a shell command begins executing, it has access to the following three files.
First of all, there's std-ear-not-standard-input.
The default standard input is the keyboard.
std-out is standard output and the default is the screen.
And std-err is standard error where the default is also the screen.
There are no additional installation steps for the shell and the debugger
if the application services feature has been installed.
This diagram shows a high-level overview of the ZOS UNIX terminal support.
A user invokes the shell from TSOE by issuing a TSOE command called OMVS.
A shell user must be a TSOE user.
The network connection to the shell by using TSOE can be either VTAM or TCPIP.
ZOS UNIX supports block mode and canonical mode 3270 type terminals.
Character asynchronous terminals and non-canonical raw mode terminals are not supported.
Alternatively, a user can connect directly to UNIX by using TCPIP.
This is the only way raw mode is possible.
A user can invoke the shell from an ASCII terminal.
The network connection to the shell in this attachment is TCPIP.
A terminal attached to ZOS directly through TCPIP uses RLogin or Telnet capability in the terminal
to connect to a daemon in ZOS that will start a shell address space for that user.
In this case, the user is accessing a shell address space unique to them in ZOS.
The RLogin or Telnet users need a pair of pseudo-TTY files.
These come from the same pool the TSO attached terminals use.
Raw mode is supported.
VI Editor can be used in this environment.
Next, we're going to look at two choices that ZOS UNIX offers to TSOE interactive users.